in this video i'm going to give you some
very valuable tips about market
structure trading
[Music]
i have a summer sale running right now
you can get 30 off my lifetime trading
academy access and you can also get 30
off my lifetime discord access now the
academy includes my full 30-hour course
and the discord the discord only option
is just the discord alone so if you want
to learn my systems trade with me get
personal support back test with me get
case studies on all the trades i've
taken and access to my live trades head
over to that link in the description and
you can save 30 there if you use the
code ss30 at checkout you are going to
save around 150 pounds which is around
200 on the trading academy and you'll
save 75 off the discord which is priced
a little cheaper so thanks for listening
i'll see you in the inside enjoy the
video hello everyone and welcome back to
the channel i hope you're doing well in
today's video i'm going to talk about
layers to structure so when i say this i
mean market structure trading which is a
very popular and common way of trading
nowadays has a few layers to it that
some people don't quite understand it's
fine but if you don't understand these
layers to structure you're going to have
a hard time actually trading
consistently because you're going to be
a little bit confused as to where
structure is going at any one time i'm
making this video to clear up any
confusions about market structure and
show you the different layers to
structure and how you can use those to
your advantage what you can see here on
the chart are the two major layers to
structure we have swing structure and we
have substructure
swing structure is the overall picture
and substructure is the smaller
movements that happen within the
corrective moves of the large trend now
what we can actually do is trade with
the swing structure but we can also
trade with the substructure in a kind of
counter trend fashion now one thing to
note about all of this is it's going to
change and you're going to have to adapt
to this over different time frames so
swing structure can be considered as for
example the hourly and the substructure
to the hourly swing trend is probably
going to be around the 15 minute five
minute time frame however the hourly
trend may be within itself substructure
of a daily trend and so on so you do
have to make sure that you are following
closely the time frames that matter to
you if you're a swing trader and you
only trade the daily weekly and four
hour the daily and the weekly are
probably going to show you your swing
structure and you'll be able to dig into
the substructure on the four hour time
frame however if you are a day trader
your swing structure may be on the
hourly and four hour and then from there
your substructure movements may happen
on five minute and one minute so that is
a brief explanation of the layers of
structure swing structure and
substructure and an explanation of how
they change across different time frames
now what we're going to do is go to the
markets we're going to look at gbp usd
for this example i'm going to break down
a few different approaches to the swing
structure and the substructure and show
you what i mean live on the charts so
first of all looking at the hourly time
frame zoomed out here what can we see
well we can see a downtrend right
because we have here a lower low we have
another lower low here
and that's broken through into this
lower low that we are now in paired with
that we also have this lower high this
lower high and previous lower highs as
well
so the hourly swing trend would be
bearish and the swing structure would be
identified like this so this
substructure is going to take place
within here and as you can see we have
kind of an uptrend of its own happening
right here in this structure
so what you would want to do is
obviously if you were following the
larger trend you'd only be looking for
cells but when we start to break
structure up like we did here
this is where we could then get involved
in substructure now some people get a
bit confused when trading counter trend
in my opinion counter trend doesn't
really exist because there's always a
pro trend that you can follow
so at this point after breaking the
structure we have a higher high then we
came down and formed a higher low this
came in around this demand zone
therefore this could have been a
pro-trend bullish buy
now obviously we know that the swing
trend
started here ended here and the swing
trend once again started here and ended
here so if we are trading this
substructure we should only be looking
to trade to a lower point than the
previous lower high so what i mean by
this is this is the previous lower high
right
um if we are going to be buying through
this trend as we can safely do we want
to make sure that we are not combating
this high because if we think about this
the only buy that we are getting here is
through corrective structure we're not
actually looking to buy into new highs
because we would then be fighting the
trend with the trend being bearish from
this lower high lower low and then
obviously the previous lower high and
lower low beforehand
so we can safely buy from here and it
would be a pro trend buy but we should
be stopping here now why would we stop
here this is the final imbalance supply
at the top of the move and if the price
did push through here we could still
stay valid on short because
we haven't broke this high
if we were to break above this high that
would then reshift the whole trend
structure and the swing structure would
no longer be bearish but it would be
bullish so at this point we could then
start looking for the larger buys up
towards you know
larger areas of imbalance but unless
that happens we can assume most of the
time that we are going to then follow in
the tracks of the swing structure
meaning when we have reached the kind of
extreme point of the swing structure
down move we're probably going to
reverse once again and make a new swing
structure down move as we did so
understanding the difference here
basically guides you on which way you
can trade and stops you getting confused
about the trend
we know that this whole move is swing
structure we have bearish swing
structure but within that there are
going to be corrective moves this is the
major corrective move and this was
indicated by this first break of
structure so when we get this break we
can say okay well the hourly is down but
here the hourly substructure point is
actually bullish because we've had this
hourly breaker structure so we could now
look to buy until the market reverses
buyers could take us towards this point
here and obviously as previously
mentioned if this did not hold up we
could then look for continuation buys so
here we can see a demand zone a big push
through this
and then that reopens these higher areas
of imbalance so we could actually look
at buys from this demand zone which as
you see would come in here taking us
towards here this would be the extreme
so we would no longer look to trade to
the upside so within every different
time frame within every different trend
we do have swing structure and
substructure and they are going to be
very valuable now breaking this down to
what i said before this can actually be
adapted into much lower time frames
right this is fractal so we can see the
same thing on multiple time frames and
it's going to show us pretty much
exactly what we want to see so as an
explanation then if we were to go to
this small area of structure here we
could see that even though we are
bearish the substructure is obviously
bearish if we were then to look at each
swing we have bearish move corrective
move bearish move corrective move
bearish move so this is going to be the
swing structure of this kind of lower
timeframe price and this is the
substructure the corrective moves
through that
now if we were to look for example at
this price action here we could say okay
well at this point we've broken up to a
higher high
so we could look for a pull back in buy
from demand take this towards the next
supply which would be around this point
then we would close out our trades and
sell into the next swing structure move
so you can see once again the same
pattern repeating where we have the
swing structure then the substructure
here
that closes out as supply then we have
the next leg of swing structure right so
it's fractal it's entirely fractal you
don't have to be trading hourly like i
am here this is going to work on the
daily chart this will work on the one
minute chart uh whatever time frame you
go to you're going to see the same kind
of patterns but understanding that
difference between substructure and
swing structure being able to identify
the overall swing structure picture of
the market and then understanding where
you should stop trading to in the
substructure is going to help you from
getting caught up in those kind of
counter trend moves so some people would
never take a trade like the one we've
covered here because they would say well
this is obviously
counter trend right the trend is
obviously down so why would we be buying
well the thing i said to that is it's
obviously not down anymore we've broken
down we've made this low but now we've
broken up so we can safely trade on the
way up here but we should never look to
extend those buyers past this high here
because the chances are we're going to
reverse before we get there and sell off
we should only look to trade past this
high once we have broken this high so if
we were to break above we could then
look for pullbacks and those would be
much larger buys but most of the time we
are actually just going to cap out
continue with the swing structure and
sell off back down so let's take a look
at a live example around where price is
now if we go to the hourly we can once
again identify things from a swing and
substructure point of view
so here we can see the swing structure
has pushed down so large swing structure
is going to be bearish
if we then look at the hourly trend that
we've got going on right now we have had
a breaker structure here
that has broken us into bullish
structure right so from this point we
can consider okay so this has actually
opened the doors to a substructure
uptrend uh this being the obviously
swing down move now we've broken up so
we could look for
all right this is the kind of move we've
had right so we could now look for some
buys but we obviously wouldn't want to
target past the swing structure high so
what we could do is well first of all we
could obviously just target this point
here
that's going to be a safe trade as you
can see buy came in from demand took us
all the way into there
but we should never be looking to buy
for example past this point here so any
buyers that we do take should stop there
and shouldn't go any higher um obviously
we want to consider imbalances and
things like that as well and supply
zones because these will cap price if we
think about it this is still primarily
bearish right but the structure here on
the low time frame suggests that we may
have a buying opportunity for some time
so what we could actually look to do is
buy up towards for example this point
here
or maybe this point here we'd basically
be looking for clear and balanced supply
zones to target for buyers so if we were
to get a buy on we can see whether
structure is still bullish so let's say
market comes down towards this demand we
could then look for a buy to here
if this broke we could look for a buy to
here
if this broke we could even look for a
buy higher but chances are you know
within the trend within the swing
structure we probably will eventually
flip back down and continue to make a
lower low which would be the swing
structure movement continuing so that
hourly trend that we've been looking at
lower high lower low lower high lower
low we could now be looking for a new
lower high to lead into a lower low and
that is what we are talking about when i
talk about layers of structure to recap
i might have just been talking about
there are two key types of structure
swing structure and substructure swing
stretches the large pro trend move up
substructure is going to be a smaller
downtrend which is also pro trend but on
a lower time frame so swing structure
leads the market substructure does give
opportunities as well and this is how we
know that we are safely trading
countertrend so in order for
substructure moves to be valid we need
to see some you know clear confirmations
we can't just be yoloing into every
bottom in the market but let's say this
is our hourly swing trend move down we
have a few of these you know small
corrections in there if we are showing a
meaningful hourly break after forming a
lower low we would then see okay we have
a higher high we could then look to buy
pro trend until major areas of supply
never passed this point and then when we
get to this point if we were to see a
flip back down this is where we could
sell in for the larger movements to
continue the trend down the difference
between the substructure moves and the
swing structure moves is that swing
structure moves can be extended far past
the low of the previous swing move with
substructure movements we are only
looking to trade through the previous
leg of price action so we are only
looking to for example buy it from here
into here or if it was the other way
around we would only be looking to sell
from here down into here whereas the buy
that then came in could extend much
further because this is the larger trend
that is all for today's video going
through layers of structure i hope this
has given you some value i know this is
something a lot of people get confused
with so i thought you know what i'll
make a video on it i haven't done one in
a couple of weeks anyway and hopefully
this can give you some clarity and some
guidance on making good trades in the
future so thank you for watching i hope
you've enjoyed this if you want to learn
more from me you can head over to my
youtube channel there's a lot of free
videos there and if you want to go deep
and learn everything that i teach you
can head over to the link in the
description i do have a summer sale
running where you'll save 30 off
lifetime trading academy access so
whether you want to go the in-depth paid
route or you just want to find some more
gems on my channel you're definitely
going to find value whichever option you
choose let me know what you've learned
in this video in the comments and please
drop a like it's going to help me to
benefit more people with this video
thanks for watching and i'll see you in
the next one